Chapter 69. The funeral.
Haul in the chains. Let the carcass go a stern. The vast tackles have now done
their duty. The peeled white body of the beheaded whale flashes like a marble
seiler. Though changed in hue, it is not perceptibly lost anything in bulk. It is
still colossal. Slowly it floats more and more away, the water around it torn
and splashed by the insatiate sharks, and the air above vexed with rapacious
flights of screaming fowls whose beaks are like so many insulting pawnards in
the whale. The vast white headless phantom floats further and further from
the ship, and every rod that it so floats, what seems square roots of
sharks and cubic roots of fowls augment the murderous den. For hours and hours
from the almost stationary ship, that hideous sight is seen. Beneath the
unclouded and mild azure sky, upon the fair face of the pleasant sea, wafted by
the joyous breezes, that great mass of death floats on and on till lost in
infinite perspectives.
There's a most dole and most mocking funeral. The sea vultures all in pious
mourning, the air sharks all punctiliously in black or speckled. In
life, but few of them would have helped the whale, Ian, if per adventure he had
needed it. But upon the banquet of his funeral, they most piously do pounce.
Oh, horrible vulturism of earth, from which not the mightiest whale is free.
Nor is this the end. Desecrated as the body is, a vengeful ghost survives and
hovers over it to scare. Aspied by some timid man of war or blundering discovery
vessel from afar, when the distance, obscuring the swarming fowls,
nevertheless still shows the white mass floating in the sun, and the white spray
heaving high against it. Straight way the whale's unharming corpse with
trembling fingers is set down in the log. Scholes, rocks, and breakers here.
Beware. And for years afterwards perhaps, ships shun the place. Leaping
over it as silly sheep leap over a vacuum because their leader originally
leaped there when a stick was held.
There's your law of precedence. There's your utility of traditions. There's the
story of your obstinate survival of old beliefs never bottomed on the earth and
not now even hovering in the air.
There's orthodoxy.
Thus, while in life the great whale's body may have been a real terror to his
foes, in his death his ghost becomes a powerless panic to the world.
Are you a believer in ghosts, my friend?
There are other ghosts than the cocklane one and far deeper men than Dr. Johnson
who believe in them.